<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors on Alex Melemenidis&#39;s homepage</title>
    <link>/authors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Authors on Alex Melemenidis&#39;s homepage</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After earning my Diploma in Economics from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uni-kiel.de/&#34;&gt;University of Kiel&lt;/a&gt;, I joined the European Central Bank as a trainee to later get a permanent contract as Research Analyst in the Directorate General Economics (DG-E). With changing divisions in the context of re-organisations I have been exposed to various topics within the area of macroeconomics, and contributed to various interesting projects such as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ecb.europa.eu/pub/projections/html/index.en.html&#34;&gt;Macroeconomic Projection Exercises (MPE)&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ecb.europa.eu/stats/ecb_surveys/survey_of_professional_forecasters/html/index.en.html&#34;&gt;Survey of Professional Forecasters (SPF)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Through my work on data management and visualisation in the ECB I was exposed to various tools and programming languages and discovered my passion for making processes more efficient. To further develop my skills in this direction and also get to know other methods of data analysis outside the realm of economics, I decided to persue a second degree in Big Data &amp;amp; Business Analytics while working part-time.&lt;br&gt;
In my free time I like to travel, do sports (like paddling in a dragon boat) and document these activities through video editing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Ford</title>
      <link>/authors/robert-ford/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/robert-ford/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
